Register of the Lorenzo Sherwood Sabin, Jr. papers, 1909-1978
Hoover Institution Archives
Lorenzo Sherwood Sabin, Jr. papers
1909-1978
80120
Hoover Institution Archives
5 manuscript boxes, 2 envelopes (2.2 linear feet)
Memoirs and other writings, correspondence, orders, and memoranda relating to American naval operations in the Atlantic during World War II, the evacuation of North Vietnamese refugees to South Vietnam in 1954, and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization.
Sabin, Lorenzo Sherwood, Jr., 1899-
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1980.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1899 May 23 Born, Dallas, Texas
1921 B.S., U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis
1930 Naval engineer, U.S. Navy Postgraduate School, ordnance engineering
1941 Staff gunnery officer, U.S.S. Maryland, Pearl Harbor
1942 Commander, LCI (L) Flotilla Two
1943 Commander, Landing Craft Groups, Tunisian, Sicilian, and Solarno campaigns
1944 Commander, Assault Convoy, Force 0, assault on Normandy
1948 Promoted, Rear Admiral
1954 Commander, Sea Lift, Operation Passage to Freedom
1955 Awarded, Distinguished Service Medal Awarded, Legion D'Honneur
1956 Promoted, Vice Admiral
1957-1961 Chief of Staff, Supreme Allied Commander, Atlantic, NATO
1961 Retired
Scope and Content of Collection
Memoirs and other writings, correspondence, orders, and memoranda relating to American naval operations in the Atlantic during World War II, the evacuation of North Vietnamese refugees to South Vietnam in 1954, and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization.
North Atlantic Treaty Organization.; United States. Navy--Officers; Indochinese War, 1946-1954.; Refugees.; United States--Armed Forces.; United States--Defenses.; Vietnam.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1927-1961 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical data, personal records, correspondence, orders, and other records relating to the career of Lorenzo S. Sabin, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Awards
    Memoranda, congratulatory correspondence, and certificates. Typescript copies.
    - General
    - Distinguished Service Medal, 1955
    - Legion D'Honneur, 1955
  - Biographical sketches, Typescript copies.
  - Orders
    Memoranda and correspondence re appointments, promotion, and change of duties. Typescript copies.
    - General
    - Promotion to flag rank, 1948
    - Appointment, Chief of Staff, Supreme Allied Commander, Atlantic, NATO, 1957-1961
  - Retirement, 1961
    Congratulatory correspondence.
- Correspondence File, 1930-1976 (Boxes 1-2)
  Correspondence of Lorenzo S. Sabin, arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - General (Box 1)
  - Adrian, R. N.
  - Alsop, Joseph
  - Ancell, Robert M., Jr.
  - Anderson, E. Robert
  - Anderson, W. S.
  - Arnheiter, Marc
  - Barry, R. H.
  - Burke, Arleigh
  - Callaghan, William M.
  - Cawdry, James
  - Clark, Mark W.
  - Clarey, Bernard A.
  - Cluverious, W. T.
  - Coale, Griffith B.
  - Cole, W. Sterling
  - Columbia Broadcasting Company
  - Cooke, C. M.
  - Coop, F. R.
  - Copley, James S.
  - D'Alfonso, John
  - Dobson, B. M.
  - Durthaller
  - Dwight D. Eisenhower Library, Abilene, Kansas
  - Dyer, G. C.
  - Eaker, Ira C.
  - Eliot, George Fielding
  - Folk, Winston
  - Gallery, D. V.
  - Gilmore, Horace W.
  - Hansen, Paul
  - Hardison
  - Helms, Jesse
  - Hildring, J. H.
  - Hill, Jim Dan
  - Hooper, Edwin B.
  - Imlay, M. H.
  - Island Publications
  - KABC, Hollywood (Box 2)
  - Kim, Tai Sun
  - Kitchen, Etta Belle
  - Kitts, W. A.
  - Korean Embassy, Washington, D.C.
  - Krulak, V. H.
  - Lawrence, David
  - Loeb, William
  - Low, F. S.
  - Lee, Hi Jung
  - Mason, John T.
  - Matayoshi, Mitsuko
  - MacGee, A. Ernest
  - Matropolis, Andrew
  - McCloy, John J.
  - McCollum, A. H.
  - McCrea, John L.
  - Mountbatten, Lord Louis
  - Murfin, O. G.
  - Nimitz, Chester W.
  - Oliver, G. N.
  - Peterson, H. W.
  - Petersen, W. F.
  - Pheiffer, William T.
  - Pye, W. S.
  - Rhee, Syngman
  - Richardson, James O.
  - Robinson, Hugh M.
  - Rockefeller, John D., III
  - Roon, Leo
  - Rummel, R. J.
  - Rust, Joseph
  - Ryan, C. E.
  - San Diego Union
  - Schulgen, George F.
  - Schuyler, C. V. R.
  - Seidel, William
  - Sharp, U. S. G.
  - Smith, H. P.
  - Smith, Robert L.
  - South African Press and Information Office
  - Spruance, Raymond A.
  - Stewart, Floyd W.
  - Stone, G. L. P.
  - Stroop, P. D.
  - Stull, John
  - Stump, F. B.
  - Taft, Helen H.
  - Thomas, Leonard E.
  - Tong, Hollington K.
  - U.S. Naval Institute Proceedings
  - U.S. Office of the President
  - Vanderbilt, William H.
  - Vardaman, James Kimble
  - Wall, R. M.
  - Wright, Jerauld
  - Zumwalt, E. R.
- Speeches and Writings, 1947-1978 (Boxes 2-4)
  Drafts and printed copies of articles, autobiographical reminiscences, and memoranda, arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Untitled speech, conference, U.S. Atlantic Fleet, Norfolk, Virginia, 1956 December 18; Typescript (carbon copy). (Box 2)
  - Untitled speech, Pearl Harbor Survivors Association, San Diego, 1977 December 4; Typescript.
  - "Amphibian Means Action," Phiblant Information Bulletin, 1957 January 1; Printed copy.
  - Autobiographical notes, undated; Handwritten transcript.
  - "Biography of Vice Admiral L. S. Sabin, Transcribed and Edited from Taped Interviews by Commander E. B. Kitchen,", 1970; Annotated typescript.
    - Interview # 1
      - Draft A
      - Draft B
      - Draft C (Box 3)
    - Interview # 2
    - Interview # 3
    - Interview # 4
    - Interview # 5
  - "Deep Selections," Proceedings, U.S. Naval Institute, 1960 March
    Typescript copy, printed copy, and related correspondence.
  - Letter to the editor, Proceedings, U.S. Naval Institute, 1973 November; Printed copy.
  - Letter to the editor, San Diego Union, re free press, 1977 July 23; Printed copies.
  - Memorandum re performance of duty, 1947 October 31; Mimeographed copy.
  - Memorandum re enlistment rates, 1954 October 5; Typescript.
  - "Omaha Beach," Shipmate, 1969 June
    Printed copy and related correspondence.
  - "Our Involvement in Southeast Asia--An Assessment,", undated; Typescript.
  - "The Panama Canal--Is It Ours?--Do We Need It?," Examiner, 1976 May 26; Printed copy.
  - "Personal War Notes--LCI (L) Flotilla Two Operations,", undated (Box 4)
    Typescript and related material.
  - "Random Thoughts on Assorted Subjects,", undated; Typescript.
  - Review of The Luciana Project by Rodney Campbell, undated; Typescript.
  - Review of Our Endless War by Tran Van Don, in The San Diego Union, 1978 October 1; Typescript and printed copies.
  - "Rising Suns Over Pearl," Shipmate, 1966 December; Printed copy.
  - "Sentiments of a Sailor" (autobiographical notes), undated; Typescript.
  - "The Significance of Angola," San Diego Examiner, 1976 March 17; Typescript and printed copies.
  - "A Sledge Hammer to Crack a Nut," Shipmate, 1967 March; Printed copy.
  - "Soviets Want a 'Red Lake' --Threat in Caribbean," reprint from the San Diego Union, 1976 June 25; Printed copy.
  - "Tragedy of Vietnam" (unfinished manuscript), 1963-1965; Typescript and holographic notes.
  - "Unfinished Story of Flotilla Two,", undated; Typescript and holograph.
  - "Vignette of a Man's Thoughts While File Clearing,", undated; Typescript.
- Subject File, 1909-1961 (Boxes 4-5)
  Memoranda, essays, pamphlets, and clippings by others, and official and semi-official correspondence of the Supreme Allied Command, Atlantic, NATO, arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization, Supreme Allied Commander, Atlantic (SACLANT)
    Official and semi-official correspondence, arranged alphabetically by correspondent. See also: Declassified U.S. Government Records, 2016 January release of records.
    - A-C
    - D-F
    - G-I
    - J-L
    - M-O
    - P-R
    - S-U
    - V-Z
  - Stamps
  - U.S. Navy memoranda
  - Vietnam (Box 5)
  - World War II
    - Normandy, assault on, Task Force O
    - Pearl Harbor
    - Sicily, invasion of, Action Report, LCI (L) Flotilla II
    - La Vestale, report on French submarine
- Photograph File, 1943, undated (Photo file)
  52 prints.
  - 15 prints of Lorenzo S. Sabin, undated (Envelope A)
  - 37 prints of North Africa, LCI (L) Flotilla II, and other scenes of World War II, 1943 (Envelope B)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1951-1960 (Box 5)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Includes some interfiled, unclassified government records. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 January release of records, 1951, 1954, 1958-1960
    Correspondence and memoranda (some neither to nor from Sabin) relating to the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO), Supreme Allied Commander, Atlantic (SACLANT) and the Department of the Navy.